<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Analysis</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Analysis</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>
      <p>This page provides data on the relationship between CDLI and
      AP24. It provides the basis for developing AP24 into a proposal
      that is thoroughly grounded in existing PC corpus-building
      practice, i.e., PC25.</p>

      <esp:h>AP24 Characters Not Used in CDLI-tc</esp:h>

      <esp:sh>Non-contrastive Variants</esp:sh>
      
      <p>The largest group characters proposed in AP24 which are not
      used in CDLI-tc are the 340 variants which are unmarked in
      CDLI-gh and which are marked in PCSL with the notation
      <code>~v[0-9]</code>.</p>

      <p>The reason these characters are not used in CDLI-tc is that
      they are not considered to be contrastive variants by Englund
      and his collaborators.  Because they are considered
      non-contrastive in contemporary scholarship, they are not
      proposed for encoding in PC25.  Other mechanisms for handling
      these variants are proposed in APPROACHES.</p>

      <p>The set of characters affected by this change is given
      <esp:link page="pc25ncyev">on this page</esp:link>.</p>

      <esp:sh>Other Unattested Characters</esp:sh>

      <p>A smaller group of 31 AP24 characters are not attested in
      CDLI-tc for various reasons; see <esp:link page="pc25ncnov">the annotated
      list here</esp:link>.</p>

      <esp:h>CDLI-tc Characters not in AP24</esp:h>

      <p>A total of 147 signs in CDLI-tc are not included in AP24; not
      all of these, however, should be encoded. In the <esp:link
      page="pc25apadd">annotated list of these signs</esp:link>, the
      abbreviation <code>DNE</code> stands for "Do Not Encode".  The
      annotation <code>sequence</code> also implies that the sign
      should not be encoded as discussed in the repertoire pages.  The
      majority of the signs not in AP24, however, were already known
      to be candidates for inclusion in a later version of the
      proposal and derive from CUSAS1, CUSAS21, and CUSAS31.</p>

      <p>One noteworthy situation is that the sign ŠU₂, which has
      curved ("Uruk IV") and cuneiform ("Uruk III") non-contrastive
      variants in the published sign lists and in CDLI-tc, is entered
      in CDLI-gh as ŠU₂<sub>a</sub> and ŠU₂<sub>b</sub>.  PC25 aligns
      with the published lists and CDLI-tc and recommends encoding
      only one ŠU₂ rather than encoding the non-contrastive variants
      separately.</p>
      
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
