<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>AP24-Q&amp;A</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Anshu's Questions with Answers</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>
      <p>This page provides SJT's answers to the AP questions asked in
      <esp:link url="/pcsl/downloads/ap24-questions.pdf">the
      2024-10-05 draft PC proposal</esp:link>.  This page is
      transient; it will be removed when all the issues are
      resolved.</p>

      <esp:h>Common Points</esp:h>

      <esp:sh>Non-contrastive Variants</esp:sh>

      <p>Questions that involve non-contrastive variants are no longer
      applicable.</p>
      
      <esp:sh>Existing Naming Practice versus PCSL</esp:sh>

      <p>It's sometimes not clear whether it's worth renaming a sign
      from the CDLI-gh form to a novel PCSL form--we have done that
      quite a lot, but there is still some value to being selective
      about when to rename.  In the answers if I feel a call is more
      or less 50-50 I've recommended sticking to the CDLI-gh
      practice.</p>

      <esp:sh>CDLI Allographs</esp:sh>

      <p>In retrospect, I think it is a mistake to introduce
      finer-grained allograph notations than CDLI-tc/CDLI-gh is using.
      The decisions made in the corpus about whether sign variants are
      contrastive or not are made not only on the basis of form but
      also context of various kinds, and we should leave it to the
      specialists to decide if further division is needed in the
      future.</p>
      
      <esp:sh>Sequences</esp:sh>

      <p>There are several kinds of "sign" which we should treat as
      sequences rather than encoding them as independent
      codepoints:</p>

      <dl>
	<dt>BESIDE compositions</dt>
	<dd>Signs that are simple juxtapositions should not be assigned codepoints.</dd>
	<dt>"DAY" compositions</dt>
	<dd>The sequences composed of UD×N followed by another number, M,
	should not be assigned codepoints.</dd>
	<dt>"AGE" compositions</dt>
	<dd>Combinations of N57 followed by an ideogram should not be
	assigned codepoints; some of these may still be notated as
	N(N57)×SIGN, in which case they will be renamed as N(N57).SIGN as PC25 is
	refined.</dd>
      </dl>

      <p>Signs that are later decomposed into sequences may merit
      encoding, however.</p>

      <h1>Answers</h1>
      
      <ol>
	
	<!--1--><li>The removed signs are either Uruk V (very, very
	     few) or Early Dynastice I/II (the majority).  Most of the
	     ED I/II are from Ur.  Now that I have compared CDLI-tc to
	     the proposal we can be sure that none of these occur in
	     the Uruk IV/III corpus.</li>
	
	<!--2--><li>From the description it sounds like the Unicode
	     and PCSL orders are closely aligned; let's see how that
	     looks when we have a "finished" proposal and see how to
	     tweak the orders if necessary.  I agree that in this case
	     we might as well align the sort orders as closely as
	     possible.</li>

	<!--3--><li>There is very little standardization of practice
	     in scholarly use of the <i>tenu</i> designation; I would
	     recommend keeping existing naming practices where we can
	     as a general approach. In the case in point, if I were to
	     change the names, I would think of AD~a as a tenu form of
	     AD~b not vice-versa (because tenu means "slanting" and
	     AD~b is horizontal but AD~a is turned). That would be a
	     double-renaming, so for practical purposes it would be
	     easier to accept that the practice of marking with
	     <code>~</code>-allographs versus labeling as
	     <code>@t</code> is inconsistent.</li>

	<!--4--><li>We should definitely have @compoundonly entries in
	     PCSL for these--I have probably already done this because
	     the Oracc sign list tool (sx) requires all compound
	     components to be declared either as @sign or
	     @compoundonly.  As the proposal goes along in the next
	     few weeks I will keep the @compoundonly updated.</li>

	<!--5--><li>The ZATU signs only rarely have other names and
	     even in those cases the ZATU name is more widely used; I
	     will keep an eye open for exceptions as I do final
	     checking.  The reason the other names don't exist is that
	     the non-ZATU names are mnemonics based on superficial
	     similarity to later SAC signs: the ones that just got
	     labelled ZATUNNN are ones where there is no later
	     analogue to use as a mnemonic.</li>

	<!--6--><li>AN variants are non-contrastive so the renaming is
	     a PCSL matter rather than an encoding one. We can
	     certainly keep all the variants in the font as a CV's if
	     you like.</li>

	<!--7--><li>Yes, we can rename to |(BU~a%BU~a).NA2~a|.</li>

	<!--8--><li>The <code>~v1</code> goes away, but yes we can
	     rename to use the 'crossing'/<code>%</code>, i.e.,
	     |(BU~a%BU~a).NA2~b@n|; the 󲱣 form is nicer as you
	     say.</li>

	<!--9--><li>This is a place where I introduced finer-grained
	     allomorphs where CDLI-tc/CDLI-gh treats several variants
	     as non-contrastive. I now think we should leave things as
	     CDLI-tc/CDLI-gh has them</li>

	<!--10--><li>We don't need to rename this one because the
	     various LAM~b are non-contrastive.</li>

	<!--11--><li>The DUG~c variants are non-contrastive, so no
	     renaming is necessary.</li>

	<!--12--><li>As above.</li>

	<!--13--><li>We shouldn't introduce a new allograph, but we
	     could say |EN~c&amp;EN~c@180| with Unicode name EN-C OVER
	     EN-C INVERTED if you prefer.</li>

	<!--14--><li>I'm OK with |EZEN~a×(HI×1(N57)&amp;AN)|; I think
	     the wrapper groupings on |(HI×1(N57)).(HI×1(N57))| is a
	     CDLI legacy--it's not needed for PCSL; we should use the
	     simpler |HI×1(N57).HI×1(N57)|.</li>

	<!--15--><li>EZEN×LA does not occur in the Uruk IV/III corpus,
	     so we can leave that one</li>

	<!--16--><li>Good catch--this does require a substitution of
	     the reference glyph. The character |EZEN~b×6(N57)| stays
	     in the proposal as it is now; the reference glyph in AP24
	     is the one that should be excluded because it is the ED
	     I/II Ur form; the one that should be used in the proposal
	     is the EZEN~b with closed square ends (I collated the
	     photo to confirm this is the case).</li>

	<!--17--><li>Out of scope/non-contrastive.</li>

	<!--18--><li>These are non-contrastive forms of a sequence so
	     they can be handled with font features.</li>

	<!--19--><li>I don't think we should rename the GAN~b sequence
	     to align with the DUG sequence; the labels don't
	     currently have consistent structural implications and
	     things are already complex enough, so I would avoid
	     adding another layer of complexity.</li>

	<!--20--><li>No rename needed because non-contrastive.</li>

	<!--21--><li>No rename needed because non-contrastive.</li>

	<!--22--><li>The differences are in both components so I think
	     it is simplest to treat the combinations as variants and
	     keep |(GIŠ×(DIN.DIN))~[abc]| per CDLI-tc/CDLI-gh.</li>

	<!--23--><li>Keep to CDLI-gh here.</li>

	<!--24--><li>CDLI-gh does have |LAGAB~axKUSZU2~b| for this so I
	     suggest we use that rather than create a new
	     allograph.</li>

	<!--25--><li>In TUR₃~a 𒯘 and TUR₃~b 𒯚 the differentiation is
	     the end of NUN which is forked and has a final vertical
	     in TUR₃~a and plain in TUR₃~b.  We should leave
	     |LAGAB~a×NUN~b| as is because it has a plain ending.</li>

	<!--26--><li>LAM is quite a variable sign but we should retain
	     the CDLI-gh level of differentiation.</li>

	<!--27--><li>No rename because LAM~b variants are non-contrastive.</li>

	<!--28--><li>It's interesting that CDLI-gh has GESZTU~c3 and
	     GESZTU~c5 but not the intervening ones. But let's leave
	     these things as they are in case the origins of the
	     current situation are probably based in contextual
	     criteria of contrastive/non-contrastive</li>

	<!--29--><li>Yes, this should be MAR@g!</li>

	<!--30--><li>Sequence</li>

	<!--31--><li>Sequence</li>

	<!--32--><li>We should leave this as it is because it aligns
	     with the ACN-encoded |NINDA₂×(ŠE.2(N01))| and the form of
	     2(N01) is the one that is standard in this compound.</li>

	<!--33--><li>Yes, the PCSL names and the Unicode names should
	     only have the non-GUDU₄ versions because GUDU₄ is a
	     semantic interpretation and we should be avoiding those
	     where possible.  I will keep them in PCSL with the @aka
	     tag; I would leave it up to you whether there there is an
	     annotation in the Unicode names list.</li>

	<!--34--><li>The actual manuscript instances are going to vary
	     in size and location of components so it is fine to use a
	     normalized/standardized sizing and positioning that looks
	     good.</li>

	<!--35--><li>Because 'tenu' is really 'slanted', but is used
	     liberally, I would not consider 𒨕 as NAB@t. I definitely
	     recognize that @t is sometimes used in this way but let's
	     leave the name aligned with CDLI-tc/CDLI-gh.</li>

	<!--36--><li>This can stay as is because all of the SAG forms
	     are now non-contrastive.</li>

	<!--37--><li>As in 36 this can stay as is.</li>

	<!--38--><li>SAG and SAG@n no longer have subvariants.</li>

	<!--39--><li>Sequence and non-contrastive LAM~b.</li>

	<!--40--><li>CDLI-gh does not consider SILA₃ with circular end
	     versus half-circle end as contrastive; they are all
	     SILA₃~a.</li>

	<!--41--><li>Yes, good catch, this should be
	     |GARA₂~a×SILA₃~a|.</li>

	<!--42--><li>I think we can leave ZATU646 as is, the
	     difference is so slight.</li>

	<!--43--><li>CDLI-gh has |SILA3~dxNI~a| so let's rename to |SILA₃~d×NI~a|.</li>

	<!--44--><li>We should leave SUKUD@g~b as in CDLI-gh</li>

	<!--45--><li>Fair question; like @t, @g is used sometimes
	     almost as a metaphor to indicate "this sign has extra
	     bits". Leave as CDLI-gh.</li>

	<!--46--><li>These SUM~a are now non-contrastive variants.</li>

	<!--47--><li>Another good question: ŠAB is later |PA.IB|, as
	     is ŠAB~a here; ŠAB~b here is |PAP.IB|.  We should encode
	     ŠAB~a and ŠAB~b and treat the variants as
	     non-contrastive.</li>

	<!--48--><li>The various sub-forms of ŠE in compounds are
	     treated as non-contrastive in CDLI as far as I can
	     tell.</li>

	<!--49--><li>This is a sequence and the components are
	     non-contrastive.</li>

	<!--50--><li>I think you are right about ŠEN~c and ŠEN~c@t but
	     we should leave it as CDLI-gh in case there is some
	     subtle contextual background to this inconsistency.</li>

	<!--51--><li>Fair question but let's stick with CDLI.</li>

	<!--52--><li>CDLI treats all TUR as non-contrastive so TUR@g is OK.</li>

	<!--53--><li>The specific N08 stacking patterns can be handled
	     in the font with ligatures; the U₄.N need to be treated
	     as sequences rather than characters as well.</li>

	<!--54--><li>As 53.</li>

	<!--55--><li>We do need to encode all of these U₄×N(N57) but
	     we don't need to identify N(N57) variants.  In the
	     question U₄×10(N57) has the wrong glyph, but it's OK in
	     the font I think.  The stacking pattern for the 8/10 N57
	     is incorrect in CDLI-gh and needs to be fixed in the
	     reference which I will do.</li>

	<!--56--><li>No variant notation is needed for the 5(N01).</li>

	<!--57--><li>We can leave this as with CDLI--I think Englund
	     was taking the small KALAM inside URU as an
	     approximated/reduced form of KALAM~a because it has a box
	     at the left and a pole-with-streamers (or the like)
	     following, so the general form is analogous to
	     KALAM~a.</li>

	<!--58--><li>I don't follow this one; the only sign in the
	     corpus is |UŠ~b×TAR~c| so that's the only entry the
	     encoding needs.</li>

	<!--59--><li>This is an interesting case. |1(N57).ŠUBUR| is a
	     sequence, and this |1(N57).ŠUBUR|~v1 is considered a
	     non-contrastive variant by Englund.  I think we should
	     not encode anything for this, and handle it in the font
	     by defining ŠUBUR.cv01 as the round variant of ŠUBUR and
	     1(N57)_ŠUBUR.cv01.liga as the glyph currently called
	     |1(N57).ŠUBUR|~v1.</li>

	<!--60--><li>Yes, another good observation.  I agree that
	     |1(N57)×SIG| should be renamed as |1(N57).SIG| and
	     treated as a sequence.</li>

	<!--61--><li>These are non-contrastive variants so we should
	     just encode 6(N57) with a glyph variant in the font
	     6(N57).cv01 and then get the necessary stacking effects
	     via ligatures.</li>

	<!--62--><li>I'm pretty sure the very long 8(N57) doesn't
	     exist; only the two column version.</li>

	<!--63--><li>Yes, the ignore vs keep is ok; we may revisit
	     later but for PC25 it's good.</li>

	<!--64--><li>I don't find |1(N57).1(N57)| in the Uruk IV/III
	     corpus so removal is appropriate.</li>

      </ol>
  
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
