<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Introduction</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Introduction</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>
      <p>Anshuman Pandey's XXX (AP23) was responded to by Steve Tinney
      in XXX (ST24) and Pandey subsequently provided Tinney with a
      revised draft of his proposal, AP24. This draft accepted all of
      the suggestions of ST24 and included a list of 60 questions
      raised by these revisions.</p>

      <p>AP24 excluded PC numerals because of an agreement that they
      would be handled in a separate proposal.  Most PC numerals were
      covered by ACN.  PC25 is focused almost exclusively on ideograms
      and includes only a few of those numerals omitted from ACN; an
      appendix on numbers provides a concordance of AP23 and ACN as
      well as notes on possible additional work required on PC
      numerals.</p>

      <p>When ST24 was submitted it was already clear that a further
      step in the evolution of the PC encoding should be to align the
      proposal with the CDLI text corpus (CDLI-tc); most of the work
      done on the prposal up to that point had been carried out on the
      basis of the GitHub collection of signs CDLI-gh.</p>

      <p>Partly in fulfillment of the need to ground the proposal in
      the corpus, and partly in the interests of answering Anshuman
      Panday's questions, Steve Tinney carried out further phases of
      work on the PC proposal in November/December 2024 and February
      2025.  This analysis prompted several realizations, most importantly
      the fact that while prior proposals had assumed that it was
      necessary to treat the entire sign repertoire as contrastive,
      the corpus and related published sign lists indicate that
      several hundred of the encoded characters are actually treated
      in the scholarly literature as non-contrastive.</p>
      
      <p>In the interim, Tinney had worked on several aspects of
      Oracc's support for cuneiform fonts and on several fonts derived
      from sign lists (especially Oracc-RSP).  This experience led to
      understanding that one of the primary goals of prior proposals,
      to create an encoding which would completely support further
      scholarship on Proto-Cuneiform, could be met partly by the use
      of Font Features rather than depending only on encoding
      characters in Unicode.</p>
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
