<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Principles</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Revised Principles for Encoding Proto-Cuneiform</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>

      <p>This page reviews some of the previous assumptions and
      challenges surrounding a PC encoding and lays out a revised set
      of principles on which the PC25 repertoire is based.</p>

      <esp:h>Background</esp:h>
      
      <esp:sh>Issues with Sign Lists</esp:sh>

      <ul>
	<li>Proposals so far based on lists, especially CDLI-gh and
	assume list entries are primary source of Unicode
	characters</li>

	<li>Sign Lists offer one perspective on a repertoire</li>

	<li>Can't assume that every sign list entry should be encoded</li>

	<li>Sign forms are abstractions; two-dimensional sketches of a
	three-dimensional writing system which tend to offer typical
	forms</li>

 	<li>Sign Lists do not define the use of signs in a corpus</li>

	<li>Sign Lists do not necessarily capture the full range of
	glyph-variation for any individual character; just because a
	sign doesn't have unmarked variants in CDLI-gh doesn't mean
	such variants don't exist (Uruk IV EZEN~c)</li>
      </ul>

      <esp:sh>Constrastive Usage</esp:sh>

      <ul>
	<li>Prior assumption that we cannot identify any
	contrastive/non-contrastive distinctions is not valid</li>

	<li>Historical dimension--Uruk IV and Uruk III forms of same sign
	(sometimes not a clear distinction)</li>

	<li>Lexical Data -- Uruk IV vs Uruk III manuscripts</li>

  	<li>Context -- commodity lists and lexical texts suggest
  	contrastive usage when they have distinct entries for
  	otherwise similar-looking signs</li>

	<li>Transliteration Practice:
	<ul>
	  
  	  <li>CDLI-tc can be used as a control on CDLI-gh: if CDLI-tc
  	  does not differentiate variants this is an indicator that
  	  the variation is non-contrastive</li>
  
  	  <li>SAG example -- CDLI-gh unmarked variants -- SAG has
  	  three forms but they are not differentially labelled in
  	  CDLI-gh because non-contrastive</li>

  	  <li>ŠU₂ example ŠU₂: ŠU₂~a and ŠU₂~b marked in sign lists
  	  but not in transliteration because non-contrastive</li>

  	  <li>KUŠU₂ example--each of the variants has instances in CDLI-tc</li>
	  
     	  <!--<li>BU~a+KI example: do not encode when the disposition
     	      of the sign is ad hoc not structural</li>-->
	</ul>
	</li>
      </ul>

      <esp:sh>Compounds</esp:sh>

      <p>CDLI-tc and CDLI-gh do not always differentiate compound
      constituents to the same extent as the independent versions of
      the constituents.  For example, KAR₂ is separated as KAR₂~a and
      KAR₂~b in CDLI-tc and CDLI-gh, but in the DARA₃×KAR₂ compounds
      the only notations that occur are |DARA₃~c×KAR₂| and
      |DARA₃~d×KAR₂|.  Where it is clear which version of a
      compound-constituent is present in the compound, the compound
      notation should be revised to be specific.  Where it is not
      clear, the compound notation should be left as is, following the
      CDLI perspective on contrastive/non-contrastive; it may be that
      variants are considered contrastive when used independently but
      non-contrastive when used as part of a compound.</p>

      <esp:sh>Sequences</esp:sh>

      <ul>
	<li>Most sequences are collections of components</li>

	<li>Some sequences are opaque, i.e., the CDLI-tc/CDLI-gh sign
	name hides the fact that the sign is a sequence (e.g., ENGIZ,
	ŠAB)</li>

	<li>Several classes of sequences with possibly different handling:

	<ul>
	  <li>Some sequences are reanalysis of originally integral
	  sign forms [esp city names]</li>

   	  <li>Animal-ages are indicated by N(N57) followed by signs
   	  which in some cases are known to be animals and in others
   	  may be assumed to be based on this usage</li>

  	  <li>Time measures where years are indicated as N(N57)+U₄,
  	  months as U₄×N(N14|N08), and days as N(N08) following an U₄
  	  notation</li>
	</ul>
	</li>

	<li>Ordering and placement of sequence components is highly
	variable and non-contrastive; relative positioning of elements
	in a sequence occurs because the distribution of signs in
	cases is not linear and is not an integral part of the
	structure of the sequence, e.g., |GA~a.ZATU753|.  The
	arrangement illustrated in CDLI-gh can be effected via
	ligatures but does not need to be part of the encoding</li>
      </ul>

      <esp:h>PC25 Principles</esp:h>

      <ul>
 	<li>shift the basis of the encoding onto the PC corpus and
 	usage, and use the corpus as a control on the lists; use
 	the published lists and corpus as a control on CDLI-gh</li>

	<li>align names with CDLI-tc/CDLI-gh as much as possible, with
	some exceptions where required to correct names or to improve
	consistency of naming scheme; if in doubt, retain CDLI
	names</li>
	
   	<li>take contrastive usage into account to the extent
   	supported by contemporary scholarship</li>

	<li>do not introduce finer-grained allograph notations than
	CDLI-tc/CDLI-gh is using.  The decisions made in the corpus
	about whether sign variants are contrastive or not are made
	not only on the basis of form but also context of various
	kinds; specialists in the corpus should decide if further
	division is needed in the future</li>

	<li>allograph notations are by default assumed to be
	contrastive but there are exceptions, e.g., ŠURUPPAK~a/b/c;
	evaluate the treatment of ŠE~a and ŠE~a@t (90 vs 45 degrees)</li>
	
   	<li>do not assume that every sign list entry should be encoded
   	as a character</li>

	<li>consider distribution of components when encoding X×Y
	versus X.Y or even Y.X; sometimes, especially for rare signs,
	it is not clear whether the juxtaposition of components is
	part of the sign structure or the distribution of individual
	elements on the manuscript. In such cases it is preferable to
	treat the signs as a sequence rather than a complex (e.g.,
	|GEŠTU~a×ŠE~a@t| treated as |ŠE~a@t.GEŠTU~a| in PCSL).</li>
	
	<li>do not generally encode sequences; this includes sequences
	which are named in CDLI-gh and CDLI-tc as single characters
	but where the naming is an interpretive mnemonic for a sign
	group such as <code>ŠAB</code> for <code>|PA.IB|</code> and
	the like.</li>

	<li>do make exceptions to sequences rule for items which are:
	<ul>
	  <li>not historically sequences but are later decomposed, i.e., city
	  names and possibly others</li>
	  <li>semantically integral and more convenient to
	  encode as characters, i.e., N(N57)+U₄ year notations</li>
	</ul></li>

	<li>do not require a minimum number of occurrences for
	encoding: the corpus consists of mostly fragmentary
	manuscripts over 5000 years old--if a sign clearly exists and
	meets the other principles for encoding, it should be
	encoded</li>

	<li>do not encode signs which occur only in compounds</li>

	<li>do not encode uncertain signs, especially those from
	unedited texts such as the Schoyen Umma material</li>

	<li>do not encode broken signs; reserve them for the PUA</li>

      </ul>

      <esp:sh>Advantages of the Revised Approach</esp:sh>

      <ul>
   	<li>encoding better aligned with transliteration practice</li>
	
	<li>additional glyph variants can be added without impacting
	the encoding; encoding every glyph variant would open PC to
	arbitrary open-ended encoding of slight differences with
	little basis for distinguishing when a variant should be
	encoded and when not: adopting the position that scholarly
	annotation of glyph variance as contrastive is required for
	encoding would set reasonable boundaries on what can be
	encoded and what should not be</li>
	
 	<li>new sequences can be added without impacting the
 	encoding; especially important for potentially productive
 	types N57+ANIMAL and U₄+DAY</li>
      </ul>

      <esp:sh>Mitigations of Issues with Revised Approach</esp:sh>

      <ul>
	<li>variant forms can be managed with font features</li>

   	<li>disunifications possible when further research indicates
   	them</li>

	<li>unifications possible if some separately encoded
	characters are later proved to be non-contrastive</li>
      </ul>

      <esp:sh>Reference Glyphs</esp:sh>

      <p>The introduction of 1:several relationships where an
      encoded character has multiple variants entails the need for a
      principled selection of reference glyphs.</p>

      <p>In order to have some level of consistency it would be
      preferable to select either Uruk IV glyphs or Uruk III glyphs
      as the primary choice of reference glyphs.  Because the corpus
      is predominantly Uruk III in date it makes sense to use Uruk
      III reference glyphs as far as possible.</p>

      <p>PC25 reference glyphs are aligned where possible with Uruk
      III sign forms occurring in published texts originating from
      Uruk or Jemdet Nasr. The selection of the reference glyph is not
      necessarily an indication that the other sign forms in EASL do
      not occur in the same period or place.  It means simply that the
      reference glyph has been confirmed to occur, where possible, in
      Uruk III Uruk/Jemdet Nasr.</p>

      <p>For sequences with multiple forms, the reference form is
      always the simplest/closest to the sequence description, as long
      as that form occurs in the corpus.  This means that by default
      the sign looks the way it is described, and ligatures,
      reorderings, or non-linear dispositions are always accessed by
      CVNN.</p>

      <p>Important to understand that the selection of an RG does not
      imply that the form is normative--the corpus is restricted and
      sign form variation is considerable which means that the concept
      of a normative form is often inapplicable to any given sign.</p>

    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
