<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Sign Lists</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Sign Lists</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>
      <p>Prior PC proposals were centred on CDLI-gh, treating it as
      the definitive assemblage of PC signs at the same time as
      recognizing several important considerations: CDLI-gh is not
      100% complete with respect to the PC rcorpus; includes some
      signs from ED duplicates of PC lexical texts; and includes a
      handful of signs which are either duplicates or are apparently
      place-holders from ongoing work on the Schoyen Umma texts that
      was never completed.</p>

      <p>The published sign list of Uruk Lexical Texts from ATU3
      (LLATU) was also utilized as a partial control on
      CDLI-gh. However, three additional lists in a similar format to
      the LLATU lists were not used in prior proposals, leading to an
      inadequate understanding of previously published scholarship on
      the PC repertoire.  Together with LLATU these three previously
      unutilized lists provide a comprehensive new presentation of the
      material covered in ZATU and need to be included as part of the
      foundational data of the PC proposal.</p>

      <p>The four lists and their coverage are:</p>

      <dl>
	<dt>LLATU</dt>
	<dd>Lexical lists from Uruk, but with some extraneous signs or
	forms from ED duplicates, replacing ZATU's coverage of lexical
	lists</dd>
	<dt>ATU5</dt>
	<dd>Administrative texts from Uruk, replacing ATU1 signlist and ZATU</dd>
	<dt>MSVO1</dt>
	<dd>Administative texts from Jemdet Nasr, replacing PI and ZATU</dd>
	<dt>MVSVO4</dt>
	<dd>Administrative texs from various proveniences, replacing ZATU</dd>
      </dl>

      <p>The sign lists are based on exhaustive scholarly
      reassessments of individual portions of the PC corpus and make
      extensive use of the contrastive notations with subscript
      letters+numbers, e.g., <code>AB<sub>a</sub></code> and
      <code>AB<sub>b</sub></code>.  At the same time, these lists
      gather non-contrastive sign variants under their respective
      parent signs and this is taken into account in PC25.</p>

      <p>The four modern sign lists are an invaluable complement to
      CDLI-gh because they represent the carefully considered subset
      of signs which were vetted for publication whereas CDLI-gh is a
      working collection of signs.  These sign lists make it clear
      that the unmarked variants in CDLI-gh are non-contrastive
      variants as opposed to the contrastive variants marked with
      subscript letter+number sequences.</p>

      <!-- ALSO ENGLUND'S SIGN-NAME-IS-SIMPLY-MNEMONIC QUOTE -->
      
      <p>Importantly, Englund is explicit in the introduction that the
      reference forms of the signs ("graphemes" in Englund's
      terminology) are only exemplary forms:</p>

      <blockquote>After each sign name a grapheme is presented which
      represents the general form of the sign on the tablets
      cited. This graphic must be understood as merely an orientation
      in understanding the form a particular sign could take, since in
      particular the texts from the earliest stage of writing exhibit,
      to varying degrees, a tolerance of graphemic variation.  (ATU5
      p.107)</blockquote>

      <esp:sh>Sign Lists/AP24 Concordance</esp:sh>

      <p>A <esp:link
      url="/pcsl/PC25/Corpus/SignLists/SignLists/">concordance of the
      published sign lists</esp:link> illustrating the reference forms
      of each sign in each one is in preparation.</p>
      
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
